<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Apollo staticus. Or, The art of curing fevers by the staticks invented by Dr. Pitcairn, and publish'd by him in Latine: now made English by a well-wisher to the mathematicks.</title>
            <author>Pitcairn, Archibald, 1652-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225378</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895843</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153484</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153484)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2367:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Apollo staticus. Or, The art of curing fevers by the staticks invented by Dr. Pitcairn, and publish'd by him in Latine: now made English by a well-wisher to the mathematicks.</title>
                  <author>Pitcairn, Archibald, 1652-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J[ames]. W[atson]. and sold at James Wardlaw's shop, opposite to the Locken-buiths,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from Wing CD.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fever --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>APOLLO STATICUS</hi> OR, THE ART OF CURING FEVERS BY THE STATICKS Invented by D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> PITCAIRN AND Publiſh'd by him in <hi>Latine:</hi> NOW Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> by a Well-wiſher to the MATHEMATICKS.</p>
            <q>Capiat qui capere poteſt.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. W.</hi> and Sold at <hi>James Wardlaw</hi>'s Shop, oppoſite to the <hi>Locken-buiths.</hi> 1695. Price 4 <hi>ſs.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>YOU have here a freſh Inſtance of the Power of the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> and of the <hi>Uſefulneſs of Geometry in Medicine.</hi> It is the Deciſion of a grand Controverſy about <hi>Purging in Fevers,</hi> that many have quibbled at in vain. <hi>At laſt Dr.</hi> Pitcairn <hi>applied his Mathematicks to the Queſtion, and has ſolved it by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod not to be imitate:</hi> As he tells us him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Learned and Eloquent Anſwer to <hi>Apol: Mathem:</hi> Pag. 5. It was writ origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in a dead Language, and is now Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into a living, for the benefit of all thoſe who underſtand not <hi>Latine,</hi> and have no mind either to be ſcortched, or reduced to Aſhes, by the fatal Flames of a burning Fever. The Verſion is almoſt literal, it being dangerous in a Thing of this conſequence, wherein the Life of Man is ſo nearly concerned, to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Senſe of the Author, or deviat ſo much as an hair-breadth from the Original. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope none will be offended with the harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Stile, which can never be evited
<pb facs="tcp:153484:5"/>in a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> literal Tranſlation. Beſides, it were an Injury done to the learned Author, to put bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <hi>Latine</hi> into good <hi>Engliſh.</hi> But if any thing be amiſs as to the Senſe, he is to blame for it himſelf: For a Copy was ſent to him by the Tranſlator, and was returned without any Amendments.</p>
            <p>I will not Commend this Piece too highly; but this I may ſay, that any one who reads it attentively, will find it one continued Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take from the Beginning to the End: And that never any one Man bewrayed more Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Inadvertency in ſo few Lines. I confeſs the Author has done Wonders in his <hi>Inaugural Oration,</hi> and far out-done all that ever wrote Nonſenſe before him: But here he has even out-done himſelf. That may be called an Original, but This a Maſter-piece, that can no more be imitate than <hi>Homer's Ilia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.</hi> It would make any Body bluſh to ſee how he ſtumbles on the very Threſhold, and miſtakes the Foundation and Ground-work of the Fabrick he is to raiſe. For inſtead of giving us out of <hi>Sanctorius</hi> the <hi>Senſible</hi> and <hi>Inſenſible Evacuations,</hi> in the ſame ſpace of time, he gives us the <hi>Senſible Evacuation</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153484:5"/>of a Night's time, and the <hi>Inſenſible</hi> of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Day, which is <hi>24</hi> Hours: (as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> cited by himſelf) and ſo ha loſt <hi>16</hi> Ounces of his Account: Which is clear from the <hi>6 Aphor. Sect. 1.</hi> But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him to have ſtated the Account right, yet he has caſt it up wrong. For he tells us, that <hi>Perſpiration</hi> is the double of the <hi>Senſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Evacuation</hi> (which he makes <hi>50</hi>) that is to ſay, twice <hi>20</hi> makes <hi>50.</hi> And ſo on.</p>
            <p>Having now determined, as he fancies, the difference between <hi>Senſible</hi> and <hi>Inſenſible Evacuations,</hi> he proceeds to open up this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, which lay hid from the Ages paſt. And from this, that <hi>Perſpiration</hi> is the double or triple of the other <hi>Evacuations</hi> (tho it be neither according to the <hi>6 Aphor. Sect. 1.</hi> above cited) and <hi>10</hi> times as much as Stool, he very Dogmatically, or rather Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally concludes, that the ſuppreſſion of the 3d. part of the perſpirable Seroſity will occaſion as great a Fever, as the ſuppreſſion of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Evacuations</hi> together: And that the ſuppreſſion of the <hi>10</hi> part of <hi>Perſpiration</hi> will do as much hurt, as the ſuppreſſion of the whole Excretion by the Belly. And for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:153484:6"/>that the promoving the <hi>3</hi> part of <hi>Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> ſuppreſt, will be as effectual in Curing a Diſeaſe, as the promoving all the other <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuations</hi> ſuppreſt; and the procuring the <hi>10</hi> part of the ſame, as good as the whole Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion by Stool. Then after all learnedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that Fevers and other Diſeaſes will be <hi>10</hi> times more probably Cured by Sweat than Stool. Which is ſuch an abſurd Notion and extravagant Fancy, and ſo contrary to the natural Oeconomie, that I wonder it ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into any Man's Head but in a Dream. For beſides its native Abſurdity, it down-right contradicts the Premiſſes, and concludes the quite contrary of what he propoſes. For he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to us the Cure of Fevers by procuring <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration,</hi> and then tells us this is to be done by <hi>Sweating,</hi> which is no <hi>Perſpiration</hi> at all. Why not good Dr. as well by <hi>Urine</hi> or <hi>Stool,</hi> which differ no more from <hi>Perſpiration</hi> than <hi>Sweat</hi> does according to <hi>Sanct.?</hi> But which is more, who tells us expreſly <hi>Aph. 3</hi> § <hi>5. That Sweat alwiſe hinders Perſpiration.</hi> Muſt we then advance <hi>Perſpiration</hi> by that which hinders it? No doubt, and the Argument runs thus: The beſt and readieſt way to Cure Fevers is by <hi>Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153484:6"/>And the beſt way to promove <hi>Perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is by <hi>Sweating,</hi> which hinders it and does not promove it at all. <hi>Erg.</hi> the beſt and readieſt way to Cure Fevers is by that which does not Cure them at all: that is, the beſt way of Curing Fevers is not to Cure them at all, <hi>q.e.d.</hi> It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows alſo from the ſame Principles, that if Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are to be Cured, the worſt way to Cure them is by <hi>Sweat.</hi> For according to the Dr. the moſt probable and ready way to Cure them, is by promoving theſe Secretions that are natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the greateſt; and ſo far as one natural Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion exceeds another ſo much the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable it is, that the Fever will be Cured by the one rather than the other; and therefore <hi>Perſpiration</hi> being <hi>10</hi> times more than <hi>Stool</hi> a Fever will be <hi>10</hi> times more probably Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by That than This. And ſince <hi>Urine</hi> is <hi>4</hi> times more than <hi>Stool,</hi> a Fever will be <hi>4</hi> times more probably Cured by <hi>Urine</hi> than <hi>Stool.</hi> And ſince <hi>Evacuation</hi> by <hi>Stool</hi> is indefinitly grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than <hi>Evacuation</hi> by <hi>Sweat</hi> (for ſome Men ſcarce ever ſweat in Health, and others very litle) but I ſhall ſuppoſe it only a <hi>1000</hi> times greater. Then it follows, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor's Doctrine, that a Fever will be a <hi>1000</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:153484:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>times more probably Cured by <hi>Stool</hi> than <hi>Sweating:</hi> And that the worſt way to Cure Fevers is by <hi>Sweating.</hi> q.e.d. The Profeſsor's Practice likeways contradicts his Doctrine here. For he tells us <hi>Parag. 11.</hi> that a Diſeaſe will be ſooner carried off by augmenting <hi>Inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Perſpiration,</hi> than any other Secretion: And in the mean time he pretends to Cure <hi>Scurvies, Dropſies, Rheumatiſms,</hi> &amp;c. by augmenting Salivation or Spitting, which is a <hi>ſenſible Evacuation,</hi> and which naturally is very little in ſober Men, in reſpect of <hi>inſenſible Perſpiration,</hi> and ſo flatly contradicts himſelf. q. e. d.</p>
            <p>More might be ſaid to demonſtrate the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this Man's Pretenſions, and the abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this following Diſcourſe: But the reading of it will ſupply that, and prove the beſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of all. But by what is here ſaid, any Body may ſee the vaſt difference that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween one that takes his Obſervations from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and one that takes his Marks by the Moon, that is, between a Rational and Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Phyſician.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Pudet haec opprobria vobis,</l>
               <l>Et dici potuiſſe &amp; non potuiſſe refelli,</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153484:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ARCHIBALD PITCAIRN</hi>'s DISSERTATION Of the CURE of FEVERS BY EVACUATIONS Read before the <hi>Colledge of Phyſicians</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the Firſt Day of <hi>November,</hi> 1694.</head>
            <p>PHYSICIANS think Continual Fevers ariſe from the Fault of ſome Liquor or Body, ſtirring up <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena,</hi> which all knows are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to Fevers; to which Body or Liquor, they attribute the Name of <hi>Morbifick Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Some will have this Matter to be an Humor that's uſually excern'd by theſe in Health, but ſo changed in ſick Perſons, that it both begets the Symptoms of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:153484:8"/>and of its own accord, that is, by the natural Force of the Blood cannot be expell'd: Others think it comes from without, calling it, a <hi>Miaſma;</hi> and being join'd to the Liquor that's naturally to be ſecern'd, that it kindles a Fever. It's not much matter which of them be trueſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they come both to one, whether the Matter morbifick comes from without, or whether the Humor within be chang'd to the morbifick Matter.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Phyſicians fell into theſe Opinions, after they obſerved Fevers to come upon the ſuppreſt Tranſpiration of the Skin, or any other Evacuation, to which the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal was us'd, being ſtop'd or diminiſhed. But the Thing ſeem'd very manifeſt to theſe who obſerved what way Fevers ended. Some they ſaw end by Sweat, Others by copious Urine, Some by Flux of the Belly, and a Criſe to come by a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, provocked throw any Glands, conveighing the Humor out of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal: Wherefore they were perſwaded, that it was ſome morbifick Matter nurſed the Diſeaſe, which ought to be expell'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153484:8"/>out of the Body, after they had brought it into that fluidity, or ſo changed it (which they call the procuring of Concoction and Digeſting) that it might be caſt out of the Body.</p>
            <p>We do not debate of that Concoction ſo much celebrate; but only enquire, What Evacuation or Secretion is to be choſen in curing Fevers, if perhaps any be to be choſen? In this Search we ſhall be ſilent of the Cure by Blooding, becauſe we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe only to inſpect theſe Evacuations that fall out by ways naturally open in the healthy Animal, and which Phyſicians aim at after Blooding, when they judge it fit to be done.</p>
            <p n="3">III. But becauſe there is an Opinion of Writers, now Famous, that Fevers ariſe by the Fault of the Ferments proper to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part, or by the Fault of the ferment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parts of the Blood: And this Opinion pleaſes Fopps, becauſe it makes them Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, and Phyſicians furniſhed with a ſtock of Three Words: I'le propoſe this Thing in the Words of the ingenious <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas Steno</hi> out of the <hi>Prodromus</hi> of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153484:9"/>of a Solid naturally contain'd within a Solid. His Words are. <q>Beſide the ſubtile Fluid penetrating all things, at leaſt we obſerve three kinds of Fluids in Animals: The <hi>Firſt</hi> is External, the <hi>Second</hi> Internal and Common, the <hi>Third</hi> Internal and proper to each Part.</q> By the Word <hi>External Fluid,</hi> I underſtand not only that in Animals which incompaſſeth the outward, like the Atmoſphere, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that which touches the reſt of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfices of the Body, that are continuous by the greater Paſſages with the foreſaid Superfice, ſuch as the Superfice of the <hi>Aſpera Arteria,</hi> and the Superfice of the way of the Aliment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore he ſays, "I call that the Inward Fluid, which does not communicat with the External Fluids, but by the intermediat ſmall Holes of the capillary Veſſels. The External Common Fluid is that which is contain'd in the Veins and Arteries in the lympha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Veſſels, and it may be in the Nerves. The Internal Proper Fluid is that which incompaſſeth the capillary Veſſels of the Common Fluid, and is divers, according
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153484:9"/>to the Places. Then he adds, that the Reaſon why in divers places from the ſame Blood, divers things are excerned, depends upon the Places, whoſe conſideration, he ſays, is abſolved by theſe Three.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. By the conſideration of the capil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary Veſſels of the internal common Fluid, in which they are only taken up, who aſcribe all to Cribration throw divers Pores, of which number I was once one.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly,</hi> By the conſideration of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per internal Fluid, about which only are converſant, theſe who attribute to every Part a particular Ferment; whoſe Opinion partly may be true, although the Name of Ferment go upon a Compariſon taken from a thing too peculiar.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3dly,</hi> By conſideration of the Solid of every particular part, to which they ſeem chiefly to adhere; who by attributing to every Part its form, ſhow that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſomething proper to the Part, but unknown to us, which according to that knowledge of Matter which we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready have, can be nothing elſe but the porous Superfice of that Solid, and the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153484:10"/>ſubtile Fluid going throw theſe Pores. He ſays, I ſhould go too far beyond the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if I would apply theſe foregoing things to explain theſe things that befal daily our Bodies, and cannot be explain'd otherwiſe. It ſuffices here to have inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuat, that from the external Fluid many ways Particles are ſeparate and carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the internal common Fluid, by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of Cribration; whence likewiſe they being ſecern'd ſeveral ways, and tranſmitted to the proper internal Fluids, by the new Cribration, they are applied to the ſolid Parts, either by the way of the Fibres or Parenchims, according as they are determin'd by the unknown pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of every place, that is included in the conſideration of theſe Three preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Things.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. But we in a Diſſertation of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite of the Blood throw the the ſmalleſt Veſſels, had and publiſh'd at <hi>Leyden</hi> the 1ſt. <hi>January</hi> 1693. Although we ſhew'd theſe Ferments not to be found in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Animals; yet that we might acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate it to their Capacities that does
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153484:10"/>not take up Demonſtrations, we are pleas'd to propoſe the whole Matter, ſo as it may be underſtood by new Beginners. From theſe Things that are deſcribed here in the Words of <hi>Steno,</hi> it may be asked, by what way, from the ſame Blood, ſo many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Liquors are ſecern'd, why in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Bile, and the Reins Urine, and other Things in the reſt of the Parts? The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients thought this was done by Attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe Sentence to explain better than they could themſelves, it will be eaſy to him that underſtands <hi>Newton</hi>'s Writings. Some Phyſicians of late having exploded the word Attraction, have committed this Work to Ferments, which they conſtitute different in various Glandules, or in divers Colatories. But we ſhew'd that there are no Glandules which have different Pores, becauſe the Artery and the Vein, no Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dule interveening, are ſtretcht out into one and the ſame Veſſel, which <hi>Autopſia</hi> or Sight confirms. We ſhew'd alſo, that the Orifices of all the Veſſels are circular, and alike. Whence it follows, that there is no place for the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Third</hi> of <hi>Steno</hi>'s
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153484:11"/>Conſiderations. But alſo it follows hence (that having laid aſide Attraction that thoſe Men reject, and which being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there had been no need of Ferments) by the defect of Glands, inſtructed with Pores of different figures, that the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thoſe proper internal Fluids, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to every Part, behoved all to be waſh'd out of the Orifices, by the Force of the Blood going throw the Arteries. And if they ſtick any where, they will ſtick in every place, making no diſtinction of the places (for there is none) and therefore any Secretion will ſtill go out by every place, having no reſpect to Ferments. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if alike Ferments ſtick to alike Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, there will be no diverſity, nor no uſe of Ferments. But if you affirm, that in alike places, unlike Ferments are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd from the Blood, and repair'd from its Maſs, the Queſtion comes back to the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> How is it, that from the Blood in the Arteries of the Liver, that are like the Arteries of the Reins, is ſecern'd a Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſerving for the ſecerning of Bile? Or why the Particles that repair this Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153484:11"/>go rather into the Liver than to the Reins, eſpecially no Attraction interveen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Neither is it only for the Reaſons here, and in the other Diſſertation mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that there is no divers Ferments pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to every Part; but that may be alſo known from the known Properties of the Blood. For what way ſhall any Part draw from the Blood a Ferment proper to its ſelf, and fit for no other Part? Or how ſhall it repair the Ferment diminiſhed or vitiat, or pluck from the gliding Fluid the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that it has not in its Maſs? It's known to theſe learned in Chymy, that no Acid can be drawn from the Blood of Animals that can excite Fermentation, or Efferve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence with the Alcaly in the Blood. And that no burning Spirit proceeds from Blood or parts of Animals, like that which comes from theſe things that ferment: Therefore theſe Ferments cannot be brought from the Maſs of Blood nor repair'd, nor Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations be brought into the Blood at the nod of <hi>Sylvies</hi> or <hi>Willis,</hi> to excite Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153484:12"/>
VI. I oft wonder'd that ſo many ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves to be beguil'd, while they glory that the Natures of Things are made known to them. Many of the old Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians aſſign'd Qualities, or a Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made up of Qualities, to every Part, by whoſe help the Actions and Secretions were govern'd: Our Authors of Ferments juſtly eſteemed the Qualities and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raments for the Refuge of Ignorance; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without Foundation or any adjuvant <hi>Phaenomena</hi>'s they were feigned; neither were they known to any but by their Name. They ſaid therefore, that there was a peculiar Ferment that did preſide over every Part and Secretion. But theſe Great Improvers of Medicine knew no more the Nature of theſe Ferments, than the Ancients knew the Nature of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raments; neither is the Nature of any Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments proper to any place more known, to any of our Men, than the Nature of occult Qualities is known to the <hi>Peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticks.</hi> Whence it is too clear from this Opinion, that nothing New is brought into Medicine, but a Word, or the uſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153484:12"/>a Word, as I long ſince admoniſhed in that Diſſertation of the Circulation of the Blood throw the ſmalleſt Veſſels.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Let us go to other things. We have written it to have been obſerved, that Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are terminated by the augmented cutanious Secretion, and ſometimes by the augmented Secretion throw the ſalival Glands, and oft-times alſo by a Secretion throw the renal Glands, or by a Flux ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perveening throw the Glands of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Pancreas or Inteſtines. We need not ſpeak of other kinds of Criſis here, unleſs perhaps you would add to the reſt the Jaundice ſuperveening upon a Fever. Then we obſerve that there are no excretory Veſſels, and no Glands ſerving for Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our Bodies (that is, Arteries termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating in excretory Veſſels) which cannot be augmented unto ſuch an amplitude, that they may be fit to receive and ſecern any Humor, that naturally is fit to be ſecern'd in other Glandules. Becauſe we obſerve in Jaundice, that that thick Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, which naturally is ſecern'd in the the Glands of the Liver, is ſecern'd in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153484:13"/>cutaneous Glands, and that too much Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of Spittle by the ſalival Glands is reſtrain'd by provocking of Sweat, and that a Flux of the Belly is ſtopped by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Humor into the ways of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration open'd by Sudorificks, and that Salivation binds the Belly; but the Flux of the Belly being ſtirr'd up again, that Salivation ſtops, which, as other Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is ſtaid by a Flux of Urine.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. In Fevers eſpecially it is to be obſerved, how oft any Liquor is carried throw any place, enlarged by the help of Art or Nature; and how that there is no Fever but the like has been terminat by Secretion, throw the ſudorifick Glandules, oftner than by any other Secretion. So that there is no kind of febrifick Matter that cannot be brought throw the Glands alotted for Tranſpiration: And though either by the fault of ſome reſtrain'd Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, or the ſtopt motion of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, or the fault of the Fluid, introduced by the chiliferous Veſſel, any part of the Blood, or any Humor may be chang'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Nature; yet this is not the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:153484:13"/>but only, in what and how much condition of fault, while it excites Fevers, it uſes to be driven or perverted. In ſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Queſtion, Experiments are of uſe, by which it is ſhown that this is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of febrifick Matter, that it can and uſes to go out by all the Veſſels; but the thing will be more clear by the following, in the which we will ſearch, what reſpect the natural Secretions have, and what from that reſpect can be drawn, proper for the preſent Deſign. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">IX. From the Aphoriſms 3, 6, 21, 59 and 60. of the Firſt <hi>Sect.</hi> of <hi>Sanct.</hi> The Excretions in the given time keep this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion for the moſt part.</p>
            <list>
               <item>By the Belly — 4</item>
               <item>By the Bladder — 16</item>
               <item>By Reſpiration —6</item>
               <item>By the Skin — 60, 59, or 40.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Whence it is manifeſt, that Perſpiration is the double ſum of other Secretions (we take here the middle quantity of Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) and twelve times as much as the Belly's Excretion. But I admoniſh here, Excretion ſtirr'd up by the Mouth is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153484:14"/>for Perſpiration: For the little Bladders of the Lungs are no leſs expos'd to the Air than the ſuperfice of the Skin, neither Perſpiration naturally breaking forth out of the Veſicles of the Lungs can be hindered more than that which riſes from the ſuperfice of the Skin. Becauſe Perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſſes throw the Pores of the Veſſels expos'd to the Air. Therefore there is no ſudoriſick Veſſels lengthned like Pipes (although we uſe that Appellation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly) in the Skin more than in the Lungs, in which there are no ſudorifick Canals. If then, that I may return, that Excretion made by the Mouth be reckon'd with Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, the cutanious Excretion will be triple the ſum of the reſt, and 14 times as much as the Belly's: Wherefore Perſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be with us at leaſt ten times as much as the Secretion of the Belly. For Perſpiration coming out of the Lungs is equal to the exceſs that any one would aſcribe to the <hi>Padua</hi> Perſpiration beyond the <hi>Britiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. Becauſe Fevers and many other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes ariſe both from the cutanious Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:153484:14"/>ſuppreſt, as well as from any other ſuppreſt, and that the cutanious is the double of all the reſt, or triple: Therefore the ſuppreſſion of the half, or third part, of the perſpirable Matter, will beget a Fever equal to that, that the ſuppreſſion of all the reſt begets. And becauſe cuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous is ten times as much as the Belly Excretions: Therefore the diminution of the tenth part of the perſpirable Matter will beget a Fever equal to that, that the ſuppreſſion of the whole Belly begets. For the ſame cauſes the help of the half, or third part, of Perſpiration, will do as much in puting away a Fever, as the help of all the reſt will do: And the help of the tenth part of Perſpiration will be of as much avail, as the Belly Excretion altogether. And the whole Perſpiration will be of as much avail, as ten Belly Excretions.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> XI. The Thing it ſelf cries indeed, ſeing that the Matter of any Secretion may be conveighed by any other augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſince any may by any way be augmented by the exhibition of a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Medicine: And laſtly ſince Secretions
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153484:15"/>proportionally augmented, keep that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they naturally had: Therefore a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heap of morbifick Matter, in a certain time, may be brought out by cutaneous Secretion, than by any other whatſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in that proportion that the quantity of cutaneous, or skin Secretion, naturally bears to any other Secretion in a natural ſtate. Wherefore a Diſeaſe is ſooner ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by Evacuation by the Pores of the skin, than by any other Secretion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomever, and that on the foreſaid Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. From theſe it follows, that a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe cannot be ſo ſoon put off by making an increaſe of Stools, as it may be by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the cutaneous Secretion, except the increaſe of the Belly be to the increaſe of the Cutaneous, in the inverſe Reaſon of Secretions, or as the bulk of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous is to the bulk of the Belly in the natural condition. Wherefore the Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Belly muſt be a Hundred times more than the Natural, that it may eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate as much in a Day, as in the like time Perſpiration only Ten times more than the Natural evacuats. Or a whole
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:153484:15"/>Man muſt evacuate by the Belly a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times in that time he uſes to ſtool once, and Two Hundred times, or Three Hundred times, who Twice or Thrice: But he who in the ſpace of a Day in Health uſeth to ſtool Ten times, he, when he is Sick, if he would be Cured by Stooling, muſt ſtool a Thouſand times.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. From the Premiſſes it follows, that any ſuppoſed Fever (and indeed the ſame will hold in any Diſeaſe ariſing within the Animal) it is Ten times more probable that it will be Cured by Sweating than by Stooling: For ſince the tenth part of Perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is equal to Belly Secretion &amp; as eaſily hapens, or <hi>Perſpiration</hi> made by the 10 part of the Skin; therefore the probability of the Cure by any Perſpiration, is Ten times more than the probability of the Cure by Stools: For it is clear that Stools are only one way, but there are Ten Caſes in which Stools do not happen, <hi>viz.</hi> as many as there are Quantities of Perſpiration equal to Stools: And therefore the expectation of Stools is One to Eleven, and the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Cutaneous is as Ten to Eleven (ſee the Writings of the Geometritians)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:153484:16"/>and the expectation of the Cutaneous is Ten times as much as that we expect of the Stools, or the value of the hope of the firſt, is Ten times the value of the hope of the ſecond. And it becomes the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Phyſician to endeavour theſe Things that will not deceive his Hope.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. We have already diſcourſed of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions that are augmented by Medicines taken within the Animal, and the ways of the Blood's Circuit. Therefore what is ſaid of Belly Secretions belongs to that, that is done in the Glandules of the Liver Pancreas &amp; Inteſtines, the increaſe of which is occaſioned by Purgatives, properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or breaking into the Animal beyond the firſt Ways.</p>
            <p>For as to that Belly Excretion that is made by Lenients which frees the firſt Ways from Filth ſticking there, theſe no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to Purging, or Belly Secretion augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, than waſhing of the outward Skin is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the ſame. For theſe Lenients only promove Perſpiration of the Inteſtines like to that of the Skin: For the Pores of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines being opened, there breaks forth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:153484:16"/>a greater bulk of Perſpiration, than from the like portion of the upper Superfices of the Body, and theſe Pores are opened by Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines cleanſing Filth, chiefly by fit <hi>Emeticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's fit here to admoniſh the proportion of Secretion given by <hi>Sanctorius</hi> obtains in ſound Bodies, in which this moſt deſerving <hi>Phyſician</hi> has examined all the Stools (made up of theſe things which went in to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteal Veſſels, and which went not in) But we chiefly diſcourſe of Excrements ſent from the Maſs of Blood by the Canals of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Pancreas and inteſtinal Glands. For in ſound Bodies, not uſing Medicines, this Excretion, by ways conveying liquors from the Maſs of Blood, is a very ſmall quantity, and in theſe that are coſtive this is ſcarce obſervable. Wherefore the reſpect that the Cutaneous Secretion has to the Belly, will be much more than Ten to One, or alſo more than a Hundred to One. What may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced hence any Body may ſee.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. Let there be Two Elaſtick Canals or Conduits, having Orifices alike upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal Diameters, let them receive at every Pulſe quantities of alike Liquor, proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:153484:17"/>to the Orifices. From theſe Things that the Elements teaches it is manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt if the number of the Pulſes in the leſſer Pipe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be more than the number of the Pulſes in the greater, in the inverſt reaſon of the Orifices, the quantities of the Liquors that in the given time flow throw theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal Chanels, will be equal, but the velo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the Liquid flowing throw the leſſer, will be more than the ſwiftneſs of that flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the greater in proportion to the Pulſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If the number of the Stroaks or Pulſes in the greater be more (that is, if the Times or Vices in which the greater Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal receives it's Liquor be more in number than the Vices that the leſſer receives its li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor) the quantity of the Liquide running throw the greater, in the given time, will be greater than the other in the compound reaſon, according to the proportion that the number of the Pulſes of the greater, bears to the number of the Pulſes of the leſſer, with the reſpect that the Orifice of the greater, has to the Orifice of the leſſer. But the ſwiftneſs of the Liquor flowing throw
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:153484:17"/>the greater, will be greater in ſwiftneſs than that flowing throw the leſſer, in the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned proportion of Pulſes.</p>
            <p>From which it follows, where the Pulſe is more frequent than the Natural, that is where the number of the ſtroaks is greater, in the reaſon firſt expos'd (as it is in Fevers) theſw feneſs of the Liquor going throw the Arteries is greater, although the Pulſe be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo leſs than the Natural, that is, if the Canal becomes leſs, and is leſs dilated. Moreover if the number of the Pulſes in the greater Canal be greater, that is, if the Pulſe be both more frequent than the Natural, and alſo greater than the Natural, then the quantity of Blood carried through the Arteries in the given time will be much more than the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, <hi>viz.</hi> in the compos'd Reaſon declar'd in the ſecond place. This caſe happeneth oft in Fevers, &amp; the Velocity of the Blood muſt be according to the proportion of the Pulſes or of the frequency. Let them ſee who are concerned, what way theſe <hi>Phaenomena</hi>'s of the Pulſes may be explain'd by the circuit of the Blood, ſlower than the Natural, &amp; aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to <hi>Fevers</hi> by moe <hi>Medicaſters</hi> than one.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153484:18"/>
Now by your leave Gentlemen, having ſpoken ſo much of Perſpiration, I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and demonſtrat <hi>Bellinus</hi> his Theorem: For none that I know, although it be a moſt pretty one have given the Demonſtration of it. The Theorem is thus.</p>
            <p>The whole quantity of Perſpiration com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Minute from a Shred, whoſe weight is a Scruple, is 1200 part of a <hi>Scrup.</hi> That I will ſhew by the following Method.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sanctorius</hi> declares, that in the ſpace of 24 Hours the Perſpiration is 50 Ounces, which makes 1200 <hi>Scrup.</hi> that is, 50×24 <hi>Scrup.</hi> Therefore we perſpire in the ſpace of an Hour 50 <hi>Scr.</hi> and every Minute of an Hour there is perſpir'd in the whole Body 5 ſix parts of a <hi>Scrup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then the midle quantity of the weight of the Body of Man is 160 <hi>lib.</hi> which are equal to 60000 <hi>Scr.</hi> or 50×1200 there is every Hour expir'd from the whole Body a quantity of Perſpiration, which is 1200 part of the Body: And therefore from every part of the ſame there will expire the 1200 part, or in the ſpace of an Hour there will go out of every <hi>Scrup.</hi> the 1/1200 of a <hi>Scrup.</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153484:18"/>Therefore in that Man whoſe ſum of the Shreds by which Perſpiration is driven is 1/60 of his whole Body, that is (of a Man of midle weight) 3 <hi>lib.</hi> that ſum will be at leaſt 1000 <hi>Scrup.</hi> Therefore there behoves to ſweat out by thoſe 1000 <hi>Scrup.</hi> every Hour 50 <hi>Scrup:</hi> or by 1 <hi>Scrup.</hi> every Hour 50/1000 <hi>Scrup.</hi> muſt ſweat out, that is 1/20 <hi>Scrup.</hi> And therefore in the ſpace of a Minute, or 1/60 part of an Hour there will ſweat out through 1 <hi>Scrup:</hi> 1/60×20 or 1/1200 <hi>Scrup:</hi> as <hi>Bellinus</hi> finds.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the weight of Perſpiration, all things being conſidered, is according to the weight of the Body perſpiring. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a Body of 120 <hi>lib.</hi> or 45000 <hi>Scrup.</hi> the Perſpiration in 24 Hours will be equal to 900 <hi>Scrup:</hi> and Perſpiration every Hour will be equal to the 37½ <hi>Scrup.</hi> Whence every Hour there perſpires 1200 part of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:153484:19"/>Body, and ſo proportionably of every part and Scruple, becauſe 45000 <hi>Scrup:</hi> make 1200×37½ <hi>Scrup.</hi> Wherefore in that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in whom the outmoſt Cuticle of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus, Inteſtins, Lungs, Jaws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> made about 2 <hi>lib.</hi> the ſum of the Shreds alſo by which Perſpiration laſt went throw, was at the leaſt 750 <hi>Scrup:</hi> or the 60 part of her Body. For ſhe died of an immoderat Iſſue or Emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragy of Blood from the Womb, the third Day after Child-birth, but her Body was 106 <hi>lib.</hi> Now throw theſe 750 <hi>Scrup.</hi> there behoved every Hour to come out 37½ <hi>Sc.</hi> that is every Hour out of every Scruple to come out 37/750 ½ <hi>Scrup.</hi> that equals 1/20 <hi>Scru.</hi> ſeing 20×37 ½ equals 750: Therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Minute or 1/60 of an Hour, there will come out throw 1 <hi>Scr.</hi> 1/60×20 <hi>Scr.</hi>=1/1200.</p>
            <closer>Q. E. D. <hi>i. e.</hi> Quod Erat Delirandum.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153484:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
